PhD, Computer Science University of California, Santa Barbara ⊠ alonalbalak@gmail.com 'n Personal Webpage GitHub in LinkedIn ¥ Twitter 

Scholar



# Alon Albalak

#### About Me

I am a recent Ph.D graduate from the Computer Science Department at the University of California, Santa Barbara, and a member of the NLP Group, co-advised by William Yang Wang and Xifeng Yan.

The primary research focus of my PhD has been applying ML methods to NLP to improve data efficiency and model performance. In my research I have explored the use of methods including multi-armed bandits, data selection, multitask learning, transfer learning, reinforcement learning, and neuro-symbolic methods. Additionally, I have a wide array of interests in other topics including model efficiency, logic and reasoning, conversational AI, information retrieval, and multilingual models.

In the future, I am most interested in 2 main directions of work. First, I would like to continue my pursuit of data-centric research by understanding models from a data perspective, developing methods that improve data quality, and improving data efficiency. I am also very excited to apply my data-centric background to many areas of ML research, including model pretraining, alignment, fine-tuning, tool use, and neuro-symbolic systems.

## Education

2018–2024 Ph.D, Computer Science, University of California, Santa Barbara.

**UCSB NLP Group** 

Dissertation: Understanding and Improving Language Models Through a Data-Centric Lens Advisors: William Yang Wang and Xifeng Yan

2016–2018 B.S., Mathematics, Wayne State University.

## Selected Publications (Full publication list)

- 2024 DataComp-LM: In search of the next generation of training sets for language models.

  Jeffrey Li\*, Alex Fang\*, Georgios Smyrnis\*, Maor Ivgi\*, ... Alon Albalak, ..., Achal Dave\*, Ludwig Schmidt\*, Vaishaal Shankar\*

  Preprint [Website] [Code]
- 2024 The Foundation Model Development Cheatsheet.

  Shayne Longpre, Stella Biderman, Alon Albalak, Gabriel Ilharco, Sayash Kapoor, Kevin Klyman, ...

  Preprint [Website]
- 2024 A Survey on Data Selection for Language Models.

Alon Albalak, Yanai Elazar, Sang Michael Xie, Shayne Longpre, Nathan Lambert, Xinyi Wang, Niklas Muennighoff, Bairu Hou, Liangming Pan, Haewon Jeong, Colin Raffel, Shiyu Chang, Tatsunori Hashimoto, William Yang Wang

TMLR, Transactions on Machine Learning Research, Paper [Github]

- 2024 Eagle and Finch: RWKV with Matrix-Valued States and Dynamic Recurrence. Bo Peng\*, Daniel Goldstein\*, Quentin Anthony\*, Alon Albalak, . . . COLM, Conference on Language Modeling, Paper
- 2024 Generalization vs. Memorization: Tracing Language Models' Capabilities Back to Pretraining Data.

Antonis Antoniades, Xinyi Wang, Yanai Elazar, Alfonso Amayuelas, <u>Alon Albalak,</u> Kexun Zhang, William Yang Wang

ICML, Workshop on Foundation Models in the Wild, Paper

2023 Improving Few-Shot Generalization by Exploring and Exploiting Auxiliary Data.

Alon Albalak, Colin Raffel, William Yang Wang

NeurIPS, Main Conference, Paper [code] [presentation]

2023 Efficient Online Data Mixing For Language Model Pre-Training.

Alon Albalak, Liangming Pan, Colin Raffel, William Yang Wang

NeurIPS, Workshop on Robustness of Few-shot and Zero-shot Learning in Foundation Models, Preprint

2023 RWKV: Reinventing RNNs for the Transformer Era.

Bo Peng\*, Eric Alcaide\*, Quentin Anthony\*, Alon Albalak, ...

EMNLP, Findings, Paper [code]

2023 Logic-LM: Empowering Large Language Models with Symbolic Solvers for Faithful Logical Reasoning.

Liangming Pan, Alon Albalak, Xinyi Wang, William Yang Wang

EMNLP, Findings, Paper [code]

2023 CausalDialogue: Modeling Utterance-level Causality in Conversations.

Yi-Lin Tuan, Alon Albalak, Wenda Xu, Michael Saxon, Connor Pryor, Lise Getoor, William Yang Wang ACL, Findings, Paper [code]

2023 Addressing Issues of Cross-Linguality in Open-Retrieval Question Answering Systems For Emergent Domains

Alon Albalak, Sharon Levy, William Yang Wang.

**EACL**, Demonstration Track. Paper [code]

2023 NeuPSL: Neural Probabilistic Soft Logic.

Connor Pryor, Charles Dickens, Eriq Augustine, <u>Alon Albalak</u>, William Wang, L. Getoor **IJCAI**, Main Conference, <u>Paper [code]</u>

2022 FETA: A Benchmark for Few-Sample Task Transfer in Open-Domain Dialogue.

Alon Albalak, Yi-Lin Tuan, Pegah Jandaghi, Connor Pryor, Luke Yoffe, Deepak Ramachandran, Lise Getoor, Jay Pujara, William Yang Wang.

EMNLP, Main Conference. Paper [code]

2022 Making Something out of Nothing: Building Robust Task-oriented Dialogue Systems from Scratch.

Zekun Li, Hong Wang, Alon Albalak, Yingrui Yang, Jing Qian, Shiyang Li, Xifeng Yan

Alexa Prize Taskbot Challenge 2022. Paper

2022 D-REX: Dialogue Relation Extraction with Explanations.

Alon Albalak, Varun Embar, Yi-Lin Tuan, Lise Getoor, William Yang Wang.

ACL, NLP for Conversational Al Workshop. Paper [code]

2021 Systems and methods for determining and using semantic relatedness to classify segments of text.

Rohit Jain, Devin H. Redmond, Richard B. Sutton, Alon Albalak, Sharon Huffner.

**US Patent 11914963** 

2021 Modeling Disclosive Transparency in NLP Application Descriptions.

Michael Saxon, Sharon Levy, <u>Alon Albalak</u>, Xinyi Wang, William Yang Wang **EMNLP**, Main Conference. Paper

## Selected Projects

February 2021 - Recommender Dialogue Systems, in collaboration with UCSC, USC, Google.

present • Actively collaborating with researchers across institutions to solve problems in dialogue systems such as explainability, information extraction, and zero- or few-shot dialogue classification tasks

• Resulting Publications: FLAD, FETA, NeuPSL, D-REX

Advisors: Industry - William W. Cohen and Tania Bedrax-Weiss

Academic - William Yang Wang (UCSB), Lise Getoor (UCSC), and Jay Pujara (USC)

June 2021 – Alexa Prize Taskbot Challenge, Team Lead.

June 2022 o 8% acceptance rate

- o Led and advised UCSB's "Team GauchoBot" in developing an agent that assists real Alexa customers to complete cooking and do-it-yourself projects that require multiple steps and complex decision making
- o Designed algorithms for intent classification and question answering as well as the communication architecture between modules
- o Resulting Publication: Making Something out of Nothing
- May 2021 COVID(ATACK), in collaboration with IARPA and Peraton Labs.

- October 2021 Mentored a visiting undergraduate researcher
  - o Built a multilingual open-retrieval question answering system for COVID-related journal articles and a clinical trials database
  - Designed and implemented:
    - a multilingual deep semantic indexing method to retrieve relevant documents
    - a multilingual reading comprehension system to find answers within a document
  - Resulting Publication: Paper/code

## Professional Experience

April 2024 - Member of Technical Staff, SynthLabs.

present o Directed the internal research agenda on synthetic data generation, data filtering, and reward models

o Developed and lead open-science collaborations with the broader research community

June 2022 – Research Science Intern, Meta Al.

September o Directed and executed on 2 projects in collaboration with researchers across the company

2022 O Explored data-efficiency through the use of multi-task learning and various prompting methods for small language models

- o Explored the use of parameter-efficient methods for zero-shot generalization
- o Resulting Publications: Data-Efficiency with a Single GPU

June 2019 - Research Associate, Theta Lake.

2020

- September o Built classifiers for automated risk detection in regulated industries through the use of natural language processing and other machine learning techniques
  - o Took multiple projects from inception to production, and developed 2 patent pending methods along
  - o Resulting Patent: US Patent 11914963

## Fellowships & Awards

- 2023 Neurips Scholar Award, 37th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems.
- 2018 Integrative Graduate Education and Research Traineeship (IGERT) Fellow, University of California, Santa Barbara.
- 2018 Academic Excellence Fellowship, University of California, Santa Barbara.
- 2018 Chia Kuei Tsao Award, Wayne State University. For outstanding academic achievement in the undergraduate mathematics program

## Service & Outreach

- ACL 2023-24 Workshop Organizer NLP For Conversational AI (NLP4ConvAI)
  - ACL 2023 Social Organizer Mindfulness meditation in a time of NLP hyperactivity
- NeurIPS 2022 Workshop Organizer Transfer Learning for NLP (TL4NLP): Insights and Advances on Positive and Negative Transfer. Proceedings.
  - 2022-2024 Program Committee: ACL, NAACL, EMNLP, AAAI

#### Technical skills

Tools Python, C++, Shell, AWS, Azure

Packages PyTorch, TensorFlow, HuggingFace, NumPy, SciPy

Machine Natural language processing (NLP), computer vision (CV), transformers, generative AI, statistical Learning analysis, regression, clustering

# Military Experience

2012 – 2015 Reconnaissance Sabotage Unit, Israel Defense Forces.

- o Engineering, demolitions, and reconnaissance specialty training
- o Battalion lead navigator